so regarding the training of the
mind um we might have discussed in the
past how it's not something that you can
do
directly um and we had that discussion
about seeing the signs of the mind which
is not the same as seeing the
mind um colloquially you might say it
that way but there's a reason why the
Buddha said you see the signs of the
mind he didn't say
you kind of grasp the mind as you would
grasp an object with your eyes or your
ears so in the same way um when it comes
to training the
mind it's also an indirect principle and
so that's one of the reasons why let's
say you have like a sensual thought or
an averse thoughts the natural tendency
would be how how do I just think the
opposite antidote it get rid of it um
suppress it forget about it ignore it in
some but in that direct sense it's just
the content of that perception or or
image that you have in your mind you
just want to get rid of it in whichever
way you can so that would be the direct
way of trying to deal with things which
is which is wrong because it fails to to
account for that indirect relationship
between you and the
mind which is kind of like um you could
compare it to a to an animal as the
Buddha did in the in the Su quite often
with an
elephant um when the elephant is doing something
um when the elephant is doing something
you know that's you just took it out of
the Jungle and it's rebelling against
what you're telling you to do and it
wants to go back you can't just like
forcefully out of some magical um technique or
out of some magical um technique or
something get the elephant to to do what
you want right away instead it's by not
allowing it to do what it wants so as
thebody would say tying it down with the
leather straps and not letting it go
where it wants that you would indirectly
wear away its wildness until it becomes
responsive to your
commands so there's
basically there's one Su that
um I think isn't very well known even
though it very acutely describes this
principle of taming the mind so it's um
Maj Manaya
number8 and um basically it starts with
this it's
um a monk asked a question basically
saying that okay if a monk just sticks
to the basics of the training like The
Virtue the sense
restraint is it that you know his wrong
views will be
abandoned and uh the Buddha says no it's
it's not just that it's it says a biku
gives up and lets go of these views by
seeing as it is with right understanding
where they arise where they settle and
where they operate as this is not mine I
am not this this is not
myself so that that's the basic
principle and then he
says um talks about the four janas and
says a monk might be might be thinking
that because um you know he's he's
attaining those states that he's
practicing wearing away but in the
training of a noble one these are not
called wearing away they're called
simply um Pleasant abiding in the
present experience so that applies to all of the
experience so that applies to all of the
Samar attainments and then the bu goes
on to say so what did what is it that or
how is it that you practice wearing away
and then it says others will be cruel
but here we will not be cruel others
will kill living creatures but he here
we will not kill living creatures others
will steal but here we will not steal
others will not be celibate but here we
will be celibate basically goes on to
all all sorts of un wholesome behaviors
that other people might do but you will
not do others will be resentful here we
will not be resentful here others will
denigrate here we will not denigrate and
so it ends with others will be attached
to their own views holding them tight
and refusing to let go but here we will
not be attached to our own views not
holding them tight but we will but will
let them go
easily so it gives these different
expositions of the same principle but
the last one really is the most
interesting one um it's called the
exposition Exposition by
quenching in Nepali is
Parana and it says if you're sinking in
the mud yourself chunda it is quite
impossible for you to pull out someone
else who is sinking in the mud but if
you're not sinking in the mud yourself
it is quite possible for you to pull out
someone else who is sinking in the mud
if you are not tamed trained and
quenched yourself it is quite impossible
for you to help tame train and quench
someone else but if you are tamed
trained and quench yourself it is quite
possible for you to help tame train and
quench someone
else uh in the same way a cruel
individual quenches it by not being
cruel and individual who kills quenches
it by not by not
killing uh so it just repeats these same
things um and
uh it's ends with that common or well
well-known instruction that the Buddha
would give that says um here are the
roots of trees here are the empty Huts
develop Janna don't be negligent don't
regret it later this is my
instruction which he would give that
kind of statement usually when he kind
of uh explains something very
fundamental to the to the practice
so as it says
there it giv that there's obviously like
a mundane application of what he just
said there that's okay if you don't
understand the dhma you cannot help
somebody else to understand the dhama
that's one of the meanings of that
phrase but you could also understand it
in relation to what we just said if you
yourself are not and and this is I mean
that's that's the practical application
of the suta if you yourself are not
tamed trained and developed you cannot
tame train and develop your
mind which means that all this hinges on
making a distinction between you and
mind yeah and um it seems to me we
should start there clearing up precisely
what we are which mind we are not
talking about to to begin with well we
already had a discussion about it that
um not to get too theoretical but um you
know the CIT would make that distinction
between Mano and CH yes and uh we
actually had that talk in the past where
we said
um that def it defines the purity of
Mind as uh when there
as uh when there
is sensuality aversion uh the five
hinges internally there is no basically with
internally there is no basically with
mono you understand the escape from
those things yes even though they have
risen so you don't act out by Body
speech and mind ex mon
and that is how then indirectly the CH
which is let's say the background to
that can can eventually calm down yes so
we defined that that's kind of the thing
that you have direct control over so
initially you know breaking precepts it
doesn't matter what what
raging feverish desires you
have uh you don't do you don't do what
your mind is pushing to do and that's
that already would start to highlight
that Gap that you know even though you
don't want these things to be there
they're still there and that that kind
of points to that aspect of oh chitta is
something that's that's there on its own
it's influenced by your choices because
of course you wouldn't be having those
desires if you hadn't been acting in
those ways in the past yeah it's not
that it's randomly Arisen you're
responsible for it but there is a kind
of delay there that you cannot like ride
way just tell it something and expect it
to to go along with it yeah so this then
shows two things like one that it is
through virtue not as an idea but actually
virtue not as an idea but actually
conducting onself for example in
accordance with the eight precepts that
will be a foundation for experientially
seeing this distinction between you and
mind J because mind wants to push you in
One Direction but now you being
committed to this precepts the whole
point of those precepts is precisely
that there sort of com between you and
your design basic which is where the
Mind exactly so nothing that you might
just think about um abstractly no matter
how much sense it makes will actually
point you to that distinction no you
have to experience that for yourself
through committing yourself to those
presets but now you also mentioned that
there is a bit of a delay so there's
also an element of Faith here and um so
even though so you see it might from the
begin not be quite clear why now adhere
to these eight precepts I'm just now
just dogmatically ABC all that well in
the beginning that's not necessarily bad
but if you do that with the view that
that that understanding will grow you
have to just take fa those precepts and
then another aspect of that faith is
that you do not immediately from the
point of view of Mind see results
because it it takes time for that animal
to calm down but also we have said
earlier that the f are destroyed simply
by not acting out which is also
immediate yeah so it's it's layers so
yes the the bodily defilements the
verbal defilements those are destroyed
simply by you not making those choices
and that's why as the Buddha said um
even at the beginning of the training if
somebody has kind of an understanding of
of that virtue they would be able to
gain a degree of of
ease um and peace from from just that
doesn't mean that it's going to be
enough for the Right View but they will
be able to recognize yeah even though I
may have these Desires in my mind just
the fact that I I no longer have to to
act by body and speech just just imagine
that just imagine like you have a whole
entire universe of things going on in
your mind but you never ever act out of
them by body and speech when they're un
wholesome how many problems would be
avoided just on account of that yeah
so um yeah so
then the point there is um there's
obviously that dimension of of precepts
and and um and and course Behavior but
when it comes to the mental Dimension
that's when people would usually think
that somehow that that that's different for
somehow that that that's different for
that you need uh
concentration technique or something but
it's actually the same exact principle
just that as you
said there is that delay and you need to
there needs to be that element of Faith
to a degree like you cannot be expecting
immediate results
because well the only immediate result
really that's that's going to come there
is is that you put the animal to sleep
so you're not training it that's usually
what what with the concentration
techniques yeah exactly so so you you
just put it to sleep of course it stop
making noise it stops uh you know
destroying whatever is in its path but
the point is that that doesn't train it
so that's exactly why then as soon as
you stop it doesn't matter how come it
was uh it's going to go back to to the
way it was before sooner or
later so
instead um you need to give up that
whole attitude of of just immediate kind
of appeasement of the animal because I
mean even like with with like a child or
something if you if your mechanism of
getting your child to behave is to buy
the toy that it wants I mean that works
for now but uh it's it's not a
long-term um good parenting strategy that's say so
um good parenting strategy that's say so
same with your mind you you can have
sensual desire
aversion um so of course uh the fact
that you don't that's where usually
people don't don't uh have the Nuance
thinking to recognize that that it's
more subtle than than just okay so I
don't get rid of it means like I just
allow it to be there yeah so there is
something in between the punishment and
reward mentality exactly yeah like you
you don't reward it if you want it to be
quiet nor do you punish it if you want
it to be quiet but rather you have to
endure mood the child might be in but if
you don't have punishment and reward
which then what are you going to do well
recognizing that it is a human being
capable of understanding things you
could for example point out the
consequences of behavior that is
undesirable then the child can come to
the conclusion for itself that it is
better to not do that and then also with
that it becomes more independent rather
than just mirroring something hoping for
a reward yeah and and in that teaching
uh relationship you would need to not be
like you know shouting and angry and
flustered because that doesn't help like
it's it's going to start doing stuff out
of fear not because not because you know
it's actually understanding what you're
saying but but just because okay I I
wanted to calm down so I'm just going to
do what he's saying but that's not
that's not a that's not really how you
get someone to to to see the um the harm
of what they're doing so in this case
going back to the example um yeah you
have a thought of ill
will what is the natural strategy to get
rid of that oh I just start forcefully
for you might not feel forceful but from
the ultimate point of view it is you
start thinking thoughts of meta thoughts
of goodwi thoughts of loving kindness
which in the surface are kind of good
like these are the things that you would
want the mind to Incline to but you
don't realize that you're kind of force
feeding those things to the mind so
you're you yourself are not like um
you're not stable you're not um aonomus
to which was going on you're still
fundamentally acting out of craving
there just to get rid of get rid of this
displeasure as as quickly as possible
and like that is what you're actually
communicating to the mind even if these
thoughts are good on the surface the
point is you are acting out of
craving so that's why it says there how
does how do you wear cruelty away how do
you wear anger away how do you wear wear
anything yeah not by telling fairy tales
not by telling fairy tales but by you
yourself not acting out of those states
exactly but not just fairy tales like
not even by being kind do you wear away
the the cruelty doesn't mean that you
shouldn't be kind like doesn't mean that
kindness is bad it means that it's kind
of
secondary you're wearing away the
cruelty only when while there is a cruel
mind you're not acting out of it mhm but
the natural belief would be like no no I
kind of compensate for the cruelty by
fabricating more kindness by turning up
up the volume on the kindness but um
well if if that's what uh you had to do
then the Buddha would have said it but
very explicitly everything there is a
negative mhm like like so so you wear
things away by that right endurance so
while the thing is there you don't uh
act out of it but you also don't try to
get rid of it it's like the simul of not
open the door you know that uh it's
outside but
you you don't open nor for fighting it
nor for letting it come in exactly so
yeah so because you open the door well
that's exactly in the end gives an
opportunity for them to to come in if
they have a gun or something well you
open the door you're done so um that's
exactly uh but see that that the reason
why somebody would be would not be able
to do that is because of that innate
kind of expectation of how do I solve it
as quickly as possible so you can't just
stay inside your room hearing that noise
of the person knocking outside you need
to get them get them off right away and
that's why then you you're not able to
tame your mind because you yourself are
not patient you yourself are not um
equanimous so that's that's another one
like when when uh this idea is like
equinity that that people would think
that's something that you can just do
but really it's not it's the what you
want is not for you to be a quanus what
you want is for the mind to be a quanus
in other words that regardless of your
choice regardless of you having to say
like oh I have no preferences no what
you want is the Mind itself not yeah
like that it's unable to to Crave in the
phase of pleasure or the it is basically
the mind that or the wild animal being
fully tamed so it is so it is the result
and that mind being indirect means that
Equanimity is not something that you can
do the closest you can do is to endure
these unome states which if you perfect
that will result in anonomous mind which
isn't moved in the first place so then
you don't need to be too concerned this
is similar with these coward like you
can just have these cows walking around
uh you you have to watch them but they
don't go in the in the in the field to
start eating crops and then you get
punished on the account of those cows
doing that yeah and uh and you would see
that actually
um because fundamentally the mind is not
yours so it's not it's not that we're
saying like well your mind is your true
self or something like that um so so
actually you know it might seem like um
like you just have to postpone
everything because you cannot be
equanimous but no like it is a form of
equinity the right one actually you mean
to Ure yes for you for you to to to have
those mental states there and see
actually and actually that's what it
says there you overcome all these views
by seeing the place where they arise
where they originate where they endure
as this is not mine I am not this this
is not myself so that's the right level
for you to see anata it's where that
mind is you know trying to push you
towards these views or towards these
Tendencies not trying to get rid of that
so that's what that's how you get to see
this is not mine because you know if you
truly have the view that it's not yours
then why are you trying to get rid of it
I was I was just going to say so it
actually already is as that saying or as
you and I also saying that mind is
already not yours but that doesn't mean
that the problem is not solved by just
stating that exctly because it is on
account of uh acting out that the
appropriation continues so it's already not self but
continues so it's already not self but
in order to actually see that one needs
to stop acting out because the acting
out is the regarding of it as mind yeah
so if if in the future so if you as much
as you might want to state that it's not
yours in the future you continue
to be be driven by the Tendencies of
that mind then it is yours like why else
would you be
following um you're identified with it
to that extent so so you need to be yes
because and this is where the right
mindfulness comes in because you need to
keep an eye on what that mind is up to
because if you don't then you will by
definition be acting out because because
that's the starting point so it's not
neutral no there is already let's say
the conditioning or the ignorance which
is just acting out which is how the
appropriation continues and to end that
is a question of not acting out so that
it can be seen as it was always already
not mine but that needs to still be
attained or acquired due to the
sufficient not acting out let's say yeah
and and it's not that it would be like a
matter of you catching some hidden
moments of of Consciousness that you
couldn't see it's um it's just asking
yourself in the broad scale of things
like in my dayto day are there things
that I still do that uh that are pushed
that that are that are imposed On Me by
this Mind through which I am still still
Mind through which I am still still
giving it the power to the side in other
words keeping it
wild so so that's how you would you
would um continue to to push that
mindfulness further not by like moment
to moment trying to to to catch like
hidden thoughts or something because see
all of that now is going to be based on
another pressure of the mind that you
will not be seeing so that's another
thing you can't just um just pick random
things and say I will endure this uh
that's why we started by mentioning the
sign of the mind so all of those
practices of wearing away would require
you to be able to to
discern pressure as pressure like where
is the pressure now actually because
usually in the beginning especially if
you haven't um you know been been
keeping the precepts for for long enough
and stuff it will be like your idea of
where the pressure that should be
endured is is going to be hit or miss so
you're going to be anticipating that
it's here when really it's something
else like when people would be sometimes
thinking that just you know forcing
themselves to go through like
austerities and aesthetic practices as
they did in the Buddhist time thinking
that no no the tameness is when I
finally I'm able to just go through this
like a soldier or something failing to
see actually the pressure is the
whole desire of you wanting to do this
in the first place because of which you
get angry when others tell you that you
know you shouldn't do it or something so
so um that's why it's it's important to
to recognize that yes the practice is is
to endure things on the right level but
you need to First have that
um you can't just like descend and and
get absorbed into your idea of what
needs to be endured and forget that no
actually I could be looking at the wrong
place so it's actually more important to
to just develop first I mean that's what
the right view is develop that uh view
recognition of what is relevant and what
is not relevant as the S would
say so are the things that are relev
can you make a
list well probably speaking the presets
starting
point but once you have that list is
there anything else that you can
well you'd be trying to make a list so
as not to well to ignore what needs to
be seen exactly Yeah so basically um
that's pretty even even once you get to
the point of sensor strength which is
the just the second step in the grad
training there's already no definition
of like specific things it says anything
that might cause uh desire or aversion
to arise you don't attend to it
mhm it doesn't give any more specific
description that so
so that's the thing initially there will
be that tendency to want to overly
Define okay I shouldn't do this I
shouldn't do this I shouldn't do this I
shouldn't do this fine on the level of
the precepts that has to be the starting
point but beyond that um well even that
pressure to Define things like you could
question that like why why do I need to
to to always have it perfectly laid out
so that I can just do it without well
that's because you want to not be
mindful actually you want to to to kind
of drop the ball and and
uh do something abandon your vigilance
basically and then just just keep doing
this so that you don't have to be aware
of where the pressure actually is
and yes once
you uh going back to the example I
mentioned um because there's often the
idea of you know meta and stuff and yes
the sudas do talk about it so we're not
saying that that meta is not wholesome
or or anything like that but the point
is you would reach that point where the
mind is naturally inclining towards
thoughts of kindness or Compassion or
contentment or
equinity not because you force fed these
intentions to the mind with like a
mantra of May everybody be well or
something like that it's because you
indirectly as it says wore away the
inclination to be it ill will uh cruelty
um discontent or
passion so that's why it says that that
those are the things that the Brahma
vhar is kind of uh those are the counter
parts or the the the Opposites of the
four bramara so by wearing away these
things then see going back to the
example of the of the
elephant like once you've been holding
it down with the leather straps not
force feeding it uh anything just
keeping it there with those leather
straps not letting it go where where it
wants to go at some point it will become
pliable it will start listening and cuz
it's just going to give up it will
realize okay this is
hopeless and then you can actually feed
it these things and it won't be coming
out of that desperate kind of just get
rid of it as quickly as I can which is
what you would have been doing in the
beginning so once you've been like
seeing again seeing that separation
between okay no these thoughts of ill
ill will are there as as in that suta
that we discussed discussed in the
previous talk and okay they're there but
my I kind of where my responsibility
begins which is through mono like am I
proliferating am I giving in am I
intentionally uh adding fuel to this
that part I don't do and that's it just
keep it there and then you won't even
have to like
um it will be obvious Once the mind
becomes pliable and then yes you can as
it says there whether to the east north
or the first quarter second quarter
third quarter wherever you incline the
mind you can get it to be just
established in an attitude of
friendliness that's genuine like it's
it's not you um like like uh pulling the
strings and grabbing the animal to force
it to move like this it's the animon by
itself mhm actually behaving in that
way so that's a that's a that's um
that's a difference between a a practice
that's based on as buha said
fabrication and and uh kind of doing in
that core sense which he said is is that
is the characteristic of wrong so right
Sam is basically when it's when there's
no active kind of um
manipulation of the mind it's factually
pliable by
itself and you will know that it is like
that yeah so you that's why
the the whole idea of like oh I need to
keep focusing on this because you know
as soon as I just
lapse um it's going to it's gone well
that's exact that shows you that that's
not pability that's just you kind of
playing this Balancing Act where where
you know the the
just for one second the the animal is
quiet but as soon as you look away it's
going to go back yeah that cannot be the
right kind of confidence you need to be
continuously on the ball and that's just
practically impossible you become super
dependent on some sort of precious
environment and then if that collapses
you realize that you're basically back
where you started and it will eventually
collapse anyway yeah
so the and the the Buddha would often
describe that permanent Liberation he
would describe it as unshakable
liberation of the
mind that's the expression that that he
would use in the S so um that's exactly
why it's
um it's not something that uh that you
need to
maintain because once that animal has
has been trained to recognize what is
for its benefit and what
isn't you don't even need to be um
consciously you know hitting it or or
yelling at it or or like you used to
before so then genuinely
um it would be just coexisting with it
peacefully uh until as as a c would say
um until the the body breaks apart so
that's that's pretty much how
it's not that you know ourant needs to
be perpetually
like uh in this moment to moment moment
to moment of
observation to to or like
um that whole view that's involved with
these meditation techniques usually that
that you know the the abandonment of
craving happens through you being um in
the present moment every second uh so
that that entire thing is still within
the same overall framework of you not
having control over the mind and just
needing to to keep it tied down as hard
as possible because any just 5 Seconds
you you let it you let it move around
it's going to go back yeah so that's the
view still all the way from the
beginning needing to have these leather
straps and tie it down but then somebody
has never moved beyond that yes so you
theight yeah you Delight in tying the
animal down yeah bit perverse attitude
which is where the Su speak about like
self modification maybe so but if that's
done with the right perspective
recognizing that this has to be the
first step it might be correct but one
definitely wants to grow out of that
because that's not yet the actual
education of the child or The Taming of
the animal that starts when it is
somewhat listening to your instructions
then you need to know how to communicate
and and basically have the right
relationship with it yeah so you would
have to you would have to gauge progress in
to you would have to gauge progress in
your practice to to by the standard of
am I actually able to just drop this
constant um need to
to
um you know re the mind in and and move
it here and move it there or can I let
go of the precepts but without breaking
them exactly yeah right so can you untie
these leather straps but without that
elephant rushing back into the forest
exactly so because many people factually
even after Decades of practicing they
may not realize that this entire
time you know the only reason why they
can have peace is because those leather
straps are still there so they they
wouldn't realize actually it's not being
trained it's just like momentarily being
kept uh under control so and it might
even be waiting
it might have even understood that those
leather straps you know because often
times people keep the precepts
conditionally and stuff like they
themselves know that they're doing this
only for the piece of meditation or
something and then once once that's gone
you know all this becomes gets pushed
aside so the animal knows that only for
these 10 days is it going to to stay
tight to the leather straps after that
it's just going to go back so yeah
so that's why it's important to to
um because that only then are you
actually as but said is the the complete
stealing of
appropriation which which is basically
bana only when you you you're not
involved at all in the in the movements
of that mind um not because not out of
the initial kind
of uh per perverted view that you just
start saying oh this is not mine this is
not mine while very much you know the
the the the entire range of unh
wholesome behavior is still there but
you're just denying it um no it's after
you have done this
training and factually the mind doesn't
incline to greet a verion and delusion
on its own anymore then you can rightly
say this is not mine e